<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons shewing the absolute necessity of large &amp; speedy supplys, proportionable to the present occasion, humbly offered to the consideration of both Houses of Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893765</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11893765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50517</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50517)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 507:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons shewing the absolute necessity of large &amp; speedy supplys, proportionable to the present occasion, humbly offered to the consideration of both Houses of Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Appropriations and expenditures.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50517:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS SHEWING The Abſolute Neceſſity OF Large &amp; ſpeedy Supplys, Proportionable to the Preſent Occaſion.</p>
            <p>HUMBLY OFFERED <hi>To the Conſideration</hi> OF <hi>Both</hi> Houſes <hi>of</hi> PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb facs="tcp:50517:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50517:2"/>
            <head>REASONS SHEWING The Abſolute Neceſſity of Large and Speedy Supplys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE have choſen our Repreſentatives in Parliament, and they being at the Spring-head of Buſineſs, muſt needs have a true Proſpect of Affairs, and need not to be told what is neceſſary to ſupport the Government, in the preſent Exigency. Therefore we ought to be concluded by their determinations, and altogether acquieſs in what ſhall be Enacted by this Auguſt Aſſembly, for the peace and ſecurity of the Nation: And this we have reaſon to do with more cheerfulneſs, ſince we have all the reaſon in the world to hope, that there will be the ſame Harmony betwixt His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and His Parliament this Seſſions, which we ſaw the laſt; wherein all ſeemed to conſpire in the ſame pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deſign of promoting the true intereſt, ſafety, and proſperity of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>We ſeem now to have a King and Parliament after the old, honeſt, hearty way of Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days; and may they, their Succeſſors and Poſterity continue ſo, as long as Government ſhall have a Being in the world: And may all their former interrupting Conteſts, turn to kindly Emulations, who ſhall be moſt inſtrumental in promoting the General Good, and compleating our Settlement.</p>
            <p>When there are two conſiderable Parties in a Government, 'tis not to be expected, but that they who chance to be uppermoſt, will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to keep the other down; and theſe will as naturally be ſtrugling to get aloft, to the perplexing, and embroyling the publick Affairs.</p>
            <p>But though this be the uſual Practice, yet, our late experience may convince us that it is not always ſo; for we have lately had a Seſſions, of about three Months continuance; wherein all things went on ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50517:3"/>ſmoothly, and with ſuch an univerſal Concurrence, as if the Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only had been who ſhould moſt effectually carry on the publick Concerns of raiſing Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both the one Party and the other, ſhewed great Moderation, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Generoſity, in waving their particular intereſts as Parties, and unanimouſly joyning to promote the General Good of the whole: And let the Men of Politicks, and deep Conjecture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aſſign what Cauſes they pleaſe, for all this calm and quiet, I muſt needs think, that we ought to make the moſt favourable Conſtruction of ſuch paſſages as produce the moſt kindly Effects.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we never were more cloſely preſſed, and as it were, driven together, by Storms and Tempeſts from abroad; that ſo we may be united at home, and every one of us put to his helping hand, to pump and ply the Oars, to prevent a fatal Shipwrack.</p>
            <p>But ſhall we unite and pack together only to Winter ſtormy Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Is there no means to be uſed, no expedient to be found, to prolong this happy Union, beyond the Time of publick danger, and to ſix it ſo firmly, that it may deſcend to our Poſterity? Certainly ſuch a Legacy would be more laſtingly beneficial to them, than all the Patrimony which we can bequeath unto them.</p>
            <p>Many Attempts have been made to compoſe our Differences, but have all proved ineffectual. Time and Reſt alone have cured ſome diſeaſes, which would have been inexorable to the beſt Methodical Preſcriptions that could have been adminiſtred: And how happy ſhould we be, if our diſeaſe of Diviſion, would yeild to ſuch an eaſie Remedy?</p>
            <p>Let us hope the beſt: May not this Truce be a propitious Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of an happy Peace? This Ceſſation has given Men time to think cooly, and deliberately to repreſent to themſelves the Benefits and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Peace and Unity; and the fatal Conſequences of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, eſpecially at this Critical Conjuncture.</p>
            <p>But whither am I going? I doubt the Reader will begin to deſpair, that I ſhall ever well perform my intended Voyage, ſeeing me wander ſo far out of my way, at the firſt ſetting out. I could not let ſlip ſuch a favourable Oportunity, without dropping this <hi>Votum pro Pace,</hi> this ſmall Peace-offering by the way; and I hope it will have no ill Influence upon that which follows; but rather give it a more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reception with all the Lovers of Peace. For, if we were united amongſt our ſelves, we might upon much better Grounds, hope, that all our Councils would be guided, and directed, ſo as to aim and center in the general Good of the Community; and then alſo Taxes would be both more ſeaſonably given, and more faithfully applyed, as alſo Puniſhments more impartially inflicted upon Offenders.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50517:3"/>
But to return from this large digreſſion, if it ſhall be accounted ſo — There are great Murmurings, and variety of Deſcants, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon the miſmanagement of Affairs; and who can reaſonably expect, that upon any great Revolutions of Government, publick Matters ſhould be managed ſo titely, and with ſo much fidelity, as in more fix'd and ſettled Times. All men think it good Husbandry (though its Policy may have a very ill effect) to make Hay whilſt the Sun ſhines, leſt Clouds ſhould gather, and ſome ſudden ſtorms ſhould ariſe, and diſappoint their deſigns. To ſearch out ſuch ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Intreaguers, and animadvert upon them, is all that human Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can do. But all the difficulty lies in the proof; which yet People will not conſider. And ſuppoſing, that this Method of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and puniſhing Delinquents, be not taken, ought we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be ſullen, and backward in raiſing and paying Taxes? Muſt we ſit ſtill, and let the ENEMY take all, becauſe we ſuſpect that ſome part of our Supplies will be miſemployed, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezled?</p>
            <p>If there be no other Remedy, we ought, in Levying Taxes, to make Allowance, and reckon upon ſo much to be loſt, and give ſo much the more upon that Account. But now the Government hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gained more ſtrength and firmneſs, we have, 'tis hoped, no need to make this Proviſion; but may be reaſonably well aſſured, that what we ſhall give, will be managed with all prudence and fidelity. But to obſtruct, and refuſe the raiſing of Taxes, proportionable to the Occaſion, at this Time, upon ſuppoſition, that ſome part may be miſemploy'd, and diverted from its right Uſe, is juſt as if the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman ſhould deny to ſow his Land, becauſe a Company of Rooks and Vermin, it's likely, will come (notwithſtanding all his Care to prevent them) and devour his Corn. At this rate he would have no Harveſt, but be ruin'd and ſtarv'd for his folly: But ſuch Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents do not diſcourage his Husbandry; but he ſows plentifully, in hopes to reap the Fruits of his Labour and Charge: And ſo may we, if we will purſue the ſame Method in the publick Husbandry.</p>
            <p>Our laſt Years Seed hath produced a plentiful Harveſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> this Summer, which may give us great Encouragement to go on: The vigorous and quick Reduction of that Kingdom, this Campaign (to the everlaſting Honour of the General, and the Officers, and to the Praiſe of the Souldiery) is a ſufficient Return for our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences in that Service: Nay, it may ſtand for an ample Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for the whole Tax of the laſt Year. 'Tis true, 'twas a great Sum, but 'tis to be conſidered, that we have purchaſed no leſs, than a whole Kingdom with it. This Conqueſt ſeems to be an Earneſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50517:4"/>of Succeſs in greater Atchievements abroad, as well as it doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and capacitate us to attempt them the next Campaign.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Levying Taxes is ſo indiſpenſibly neceſſary for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating the Work ſo fairly advanced; inſtead of murmuring and complaining againſt our Senate for impoſing them, we ſhould be moſt ſenſibly affected, with all the grateful Reſentments, that were ever due to the moſt provident and vigilant Patriots. And ſince (which is to be conſidered) we pay the largeſt ſhare of them, we ought to be convinc'd that the Exigency of our Affairs doth require them.</p>
            <p>In the Two Late Reigns, I will not deny but that we had Cauſe to be uneaſie under Taxes; ſince they were either ſo vainly and profuſely ſquandered away, or ſo imploy'd, as if they had been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions impoſed, and exacted by our Enemies, rather than Supplies for the neceſſary Support of the Government.</p>
            <p>But now we have a King we can truſt, (and 'tis not long ſince we could ſay ſo) who both can, and will manage to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and is as indefatigably intent in executing the Office of a juſt, wiſe, and valiant Prince, (and performs it as well) as the beſt, and worthieſt of his Predeceſſors. A Prince who deſpiſes no Danger to do us good; who hath freely expoſed himſelf to the greateſt Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties for our ſakes, and is at any time ready to venture his Perſon for our Benefit, and the Honour of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>With what Cares and perplexed Thoughts, was His Majeſty exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed? To how many dangers was His Royal Perſon expoſed? With what amazing Difficulties did he Conteſt in the happy Enterprize of our Deliverance; (Difficulties, had he not been conducted out of them by the Hand of Divine Providence)? And with what Conſtancy, and vigorous Reſolution; with what Intenſneſs of Mind, and Fateigue of Body, hath His Majeſty ever ſince perſevered ſteddy, and immoveably conſtant to his firſt Generous Undertaking?</p>
            <p>This is no ſtrained Panegyrick, but only a ſhort, and tranſient Glance at bare Matter of Fact, which His Majeſties greateſt Enemies cannot but acknowledge.</p>
            <p>And we be backward, and ſlow in Contributing the beſt Aſſiſtance we can give to a Prince, who inceſſantly labours, both in Mind and Body to procure our Eaſe and Safety.</p>
            <p>If we would be frugal and thrifty Husbands of our Money, 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, The way is, to be quick and liberal in giving, for ſome time, that we may Not be always giving, (or at leaſt that it may leſſen by degrees) like as Phyſitians adviſe to take Blood freely, to ſtanch ſuch Haemorrhagies of frequent Bleeding, as otherwiſe would endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Life of the Patient.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50517:4"/>
In the beginning of the Late Reign, the ſtream of Common Talk run, that every Body was willing to have parted with one half, to have ſecur'd the other, and ſtill our Religion had been in danger, or at beſt, had been depreſs'd and inſulted over.</p>
            <p>And ſhall we not be more willing now, to Contribute a Share, competent for the occaſion, ſince 'tis hop'd it will fall ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees below that. And ſure we ſhall thereby (in human probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) ſecure the entire Enjoyment of our Religion, Liberties, and Properties.</p>
            <p>To give plentifully now, is like ſearching a Wound to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; which, though it may cauſe ſome extraordinary pain and ſmart for the preſent, yet is the moſt effectual Courſe, in order to a ſpeedy and perfect Cure; whereas to give ſparingly, will but pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate, and only make an Anodine: The Pain will again return with more acuteneſs. <hi>If we ſow ſparingly we ſhall reap ſparingly,</hi> is a Text, which I think, may without offence be applyed to the preſent Caſe: But if we ſow bountifully, I dare promiſe, (without pretending to the Gift of Prophecy) that we ſhall, by <hi>GOD</hi>'s Aſſiſtance, reap a plentiful Harveſt.</p>
            <p>If any of us ſhould have a Suit at Law of great Moment, and loſe the Cauſe by pinching the Lawyers, and Attorneys, in their Fees, it would be no great ſign of prudent Management: And is it not a much greater imprudence, and much more lyable to Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to ſtarve the Publick Cauſe, on which we do <hi>All</hi> together, with <hi>all that we have,</hi> depend?</p>
            <p>To ſpend to get, is ſuch an obvious piece of Prudence, that no body ſcarce will neglect: Gentlemen, and thoſe of the higher Rank, if they have a probable Proſpect of Advancement into Offices and Places, they will ſpare no reaſonable Coſt, as well as no Pains, to accompliſh their Deſign. The Tradeſ-men too, will Careſs, and treat his Cuſtomers high, when he hopes it will bring in a Return with good Encreaſe.</p>
            <p>And why ſhall not we, (for the ſame End and Deſign) ſpend freely upon the Publick; eſpecially, ſince the omiſſion thereof, is like to be ſo fatal to us.</p>
            <p>When People are parſimonious, inclining to an extream; if they have a hopeful Poſterity to reap the Fruits of their Cares, this is accounted an Error of the Right Hand, a pardonable Fault, yet 'tis a Fault.</p>
            <p>But when People take the ſame Courſe, of hoarding up Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when they have only a Fool, or they don't know who to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: This is by the wiſeſt of Men, rank'd amongſt the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Follies of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50517:5"/>
But now further; if Perſons ſhall be ſparing of a ſmall part of their great Subſtance, (for I'me now ſpeaking to the rich Hoarders, beſt able to pay) when, in a manner, the inevitable Conſequence, of ſuch ſaving, will be, to expoſe all the reſt, to the Mercy of a cruel and implacable Enemy: This is a much higher Extream of Imprudence ſtill; for in the Inſtances above (beſides other Reaſons) the Parties would have the poſſeſſion (I can't ſay enjoy them) for their own time, of what they had ſo anxiouſly ſcrap'd together.</p>
            <p>But now in our Caſe, the Enemy would make 'em put off their Shooes before they're going to Bed, and ſtrip them of all, whilſt alive, and treat them like Slaves, and account them Fools for their pains, for being ſo Penny-wiſe, in ſparing of that which would have ſecured the reſt.</p>
            <p>What would the Wiſe Man have ſaid to all this? This ſure, is (as one may ſay) ſuch an extravagant piece of Thrift, that he never thought the moſt penurious Miſer, could e're have been guilty of, and therefore left us no Reprimand nor Cenſure in the Caſe: Like as ſome Law givers have omitted making Laws, againſt ſuch enormous Vices, as they could not think, would be perpetrated by the wickedeſt and vileſt of Mankind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>We have a good Government in time of Peace, let's mend the Defects it's lyable to in time of War, by good management, and quick diſpatch. We ſee, to our damage, how early our Enemy is in his Preparations: We are ready enough to follow the <hi>French</hi> in their Vanities.</p>
            <p>But if we muſt be their Imitators, let us not only imitate them in their airy and lighter Part, but alſo in their ſolid and manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Part too, that by our raiſing ſufficient Supplies, and good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, we may proſecute the War to Effect.</p>
            <p>There are few of the Nobility, and higher Rank, who have not unneceſſarily ſpent ſix or ſeven times as much, as they have paid in Taxes, (and in as ſhort a time too) without any Concern or Regret; and there are few of the Degrees under them, who have not ſome time or other had Loſſes by Sea, truſting Commodities, or lending to inſolvent Perſons, to the Value above-mentioned; and we find by experience, that after ſome little time, they bear thoſe Loſſes well enough, and rub on, and go about their Buſineſs, as cheerfully as before.</p>
            <p>Why then ſhan't we bear a Payment to the Publick (for Loſs I can't call it) of like Value, with a more eaſie, and leſs anxious Concern; ſince thereby we hope to ſecure the reſt, and to relieve and reſcue our Allies and Friends, from the great Oppreſſions they lye under.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50517:5"/>
But perhaps, this dry way of reaſoning, may grow ſomewhat tedious; to move the Affections and Reaſon together, may be more prevailing with ſome: Suppoſe then, we ſhould hear the raging Sea had entred our Neighbours Countries round, and how it bluſter'd and ſwell'd, and came rowling along, and threatned a general Deluge; if inſtead of raiſing a ſpeedy and plentiful Sum to repair the Banks, to put a Check to its fury and rage, we ſhould hang back and be ſlow, and each one wrangle to pay his due ſhare, and drill out the time, until the mercileſs Waves come floating along and end the Debate, by tumbling us all in the Deluge; Should we not in all this be more unadvis'd, than were the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Zealots of old? For they (notwithſtanding their heats and their feuds) would joyn and unite to repulſe an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, when at their Gates: And ſhall we be wrangling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating about paying our ſhares, for repairing the Breeches i'th' Walls, while the Enemy enters the City by ſtorm, and put all to the Sword?</p>
            <p>This Alluſion, I think, is not very wide and foreign from our preſent Circumſtances; for, tho' we ſhan't be all deſtroy'd, and put to the Sword upon a Conqueſt, yet, when we ſhall have loſt our Liberties and Properties, and which ought to be dearer to us, the free Exerciſe of our Religion too, how inſipid, nay rather, how burthenſome would ſuch a Life be to any true <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Spirit, or good Chriſtian. — Would an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Life be worth valuing or ſaving, which can't breath in a free Air, but be ſurrounded with the Checks, Inſults and Cruelties of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Tyrant?</p>
            <p>But Inſtances and Examples, which lye freſh in Peoples Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, eſpecially ſuch as they have been moſt ſenſibly affected with of late, may make ſtronger and more lively Impreſſions, than the beſt cold Reaſoning, or the moſt hitting Alluſions that can be invented.</p>
            <p>Let us inſtance then, in the late <hi>Iriſh</hi> Alarum, with what a Panick Fear was the whole Nation ſtruck at that time, and what Lamenting, what Skreeking and Crying was there heard in our Streets (with the Women): And though the Men ſhew'd all the Bravery of the Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage, in muſtering together to encounter the Danger; yet, as Men of Common Senſe, who would not be Fool-hardy, conſidering the Tumult and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and with what horror and dread the Danger was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, it can't well be ſuppos'd, but that they too were in ſuch a Conſternation, as that they would have been willing to have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50517:6"/>made a good large Offering, towards the appeaſing thoſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, fierce and ravenous <hi>Daemons,</hi> if that would have ſav'd the reſt, and alſo their, and their Wives and Childrens Lives.</p>
            <p>May we not reaſonably ſuppoſe, every body would have giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en a Year or two's Revenue, and ſo proportionable for Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſtates: And herein I dare appeal to every Man's pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Thoughts, if they would but ſet themſelves to repreſent the danger, juſt as it appear'd to them then, if they would not have been willing, to have made ſuch an Offering as above, and thought they had compounded at an eaſie Rate.</p>
            <p>Our danger now, (for ought I know) is as great as it was ſuppos'd to be then, tho' not all out ſo near at hand; for tho' a Conqueror may not take away our Lives (as above-ſaid) yet ſuch a Life as we ſhould then have, would but be a lingring Death. Why then ſhould we not be as willing to give as good a Price towards procuring our Safety now, as then.</p>
            <p>Therefore let's every one ſet apart two Years Revenue (and ſo proportionably, according to every ones ability) for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service; beſides what's already paſt, let's account our ſelves Debtors to the Publick, ſo much. 'Tis an honeſt and juſt debt, and ought firſt to be paid: And thoſe who have no Mind to be in debt, may reckon upon't as an Adventure ſent out, it may perhaps, make a Return, with good Encreaſe; at worſt, there is good reaſon to hope, it will enſure the reſt of their ſtock: All this would ariſe to a very great Summ, and not much hurt the wealthieſt and richeſt ſort, from whom ought to ariſe the greateſt part of the Taxes.</p>
            <p>But if all this Propoſal be a ſtrain too high, yet at leaſt, let it be like bending a crooked Tree to an extream, to make it grow ſtrait: Let theſe Conſiderations however, prevail and influence us, to contribute ſuch Proportions, as our Senate ſhall from time to time judge neceſſary or expedient, without repin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or deſponding, perhaps much leſs than is propos'd may ſerve.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, (if it were practical) it ſeems greatly neceſſary to lighten the Burthen of thoſe, on whom Taxes lye moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and place it on thoſe who are better able to bear it, by which means, ſuch would hold out much longer, and the great and rich ones too; and this ſhould be done in time, before it be too late: For the higher and lower Rank of Men, depend each upon the other. It may be ſaid of them, as of Old Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple much about an Age, that if one dye, the other will quake for fear. When the meaner ſort are ſinking, they will go near
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50517:6"/>to catch hold of the Great Ones, and pluck them along: It ought always to be remembred, that a Kitching is as uſeful (if not more) than a Parlour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> (a wiſe People) in their way of Taxing, had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Circumſtances of perſons, and to their Uſefulneſs in the Common-wealth; and the Reaſon and Nature of the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it: For, may not a ſingle man, of an Hundred Pound <hi>per Annum</hi> clear Eſtate, afford to pay, double or treble, to him that hath but an eſtate of like Value, who hath a Wife and five or ſix Children to maintain and provide for: There are great variety of Inſtances of this Nature; to enumerate them, and propoſe fit Remedies, would make up a Treatiſe of its ſelf; and a very uſeful one too it might be, well worth the pains of any ſuch perſon, as ſhall have a Talent ſufficient for the undertaking it: For, it would require great Prudence and Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Methinks, to Tax people without any Conſideration of their particular Abilities, ſeems as unreaſonable, as 'tis amongſt the Good Fellows, to ſorce all Conſtitutions to drink alike; whereas ſome may be Sick, others Drunk, while others again may ſcarce be Toucht, nor ſo much as Merry. So in our Caſe, by this unequal-equal-way of Taxing every ones Eſtate alike; ſome may be Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, others almoſt Undone, while others (<hi>viz.</hi> the Rich Ones) are not Hurt, nor can ſcarce miſs what they have Payd, (though it will reach 'em at laſt, if not prevented, by the means aforeſaid.)</p>
            <p>In common times, when Taxes are Low and Eaſie, the neceſſity of an exact Scrutiny, in diſtinguiſhing the Abilities of Perſons, is not ſo preſſing: But now, that the Country - Trade ſinks ſo Low, and Taxes riſe ſo High, ſure all proper Methods ought to be taken in laying of Taxes, ſo as they may continue Longeſt, and be leaſt Grievous.</p>
            <p>And if, at this Juncture, we contrive and manage to the beſt Advantage, and moſt Eaſe, to all Parties concern'd, and uſe all probable means; (ſince Providence ſo ſignally favour'd His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Undertaking, in delivering us out of our Diſtreſs; and ſince ſo many of our Neighbours labour under the like Preſſures, and depend upon our Aid and Aſſiſtance); Why may we not yet hope, that the ſame Divine Hand will lead His Majeſty on, to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes of larger extent, and more diffuſive in their happy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences? Why may we not yet hope, that the Almighty hath Deputed his Majeſty, as his Vice-gerent, to put a Check to the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages and Devaſtations of the great Diſturber of Europe, and to force him to Reaſon?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50517:7"/>
Many a ſeeming Topping Tradeſman, who bears it off at a great Rate, and who ſo much Talkt on, on the Change, as they; yet ſuch of them muſt needs have many a ſad Heart-ake, and fetch many a deep Sigh in private, who knowing the weakneſs of their Condition, to be ſuch, that in a very little time, they muſt ſlink off the Stage, and vaniſh like an Apparition, or ſhrink into ſome low and mean ſtation; Why may it not fare thus with this great Trafficker that makes ſuch a Buſle in the World? His Forreign, and chief Trade of buying Towns, fails him already: We have heard no Returns in that kind of a long time; and his Home-Trade muſt needs run very Low, ſince his highly-injured Neighbours refuſes all Commerce with him, for the Product of his own Country ever ſince he endeavour'd to Monopolize and Engroſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe are probable circumſtances to Conjecture, that things are worſe with him than moſt people ſuppoſe. If We and the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates hold together but for ſome time, Why may not this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sun with the Pompous Motto, <hi>(Nec pluribus Impar)</hi> be only like the ſplendor of the Sun when its going to ſet?</p>
            <p>But as in Hawking, if the Cramp take the Hawk (a diſeaſe they are incident to) it ſo hinders her Flight, ſhe will ſcarce be a Match for a Crow: So, if we be too ſparing in our Supplies, we ſhall alſo be cramp'd in our Sinews of War; We ſhall not be able to pounce and plume our Enemy, as we ought; at that rate indeed the lurching Rook may well be too hard for the generous Hawk. And plume our Enemy we muſt, if ever we hope to live peaceably under our Vines; for, if We and the Confederates ſhould make a Peace with Him, and permit him to Enjoy his New Conqueſts, this would in effect ſhew him the way how to gain all the Reſt: This Tame way of yeilding, would but make us Tenants at Will of our yet Fee-ſimple Eſtate. We ſhould then have no more Solace and Satisfaction, amidſt the plentiful product of our Country, than <hi>Damocles</hi> had, when plac'd at the plentiful well-ſpread Table of <hi>Dyoniſius,</hi> with the point of a Sword hanging over his bare Head, only by one ſingle Hair.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be Noted as a Defect, That I have not at large Vindicated the Lawfulneſs and Neceſſity of procuring and bringing on the Revolution, and carrying on this Expenſive War; for they may ſay, if People were well Convinc'd of that, it might be a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Argument to contribute more heartily and freely.</p>
            <p>I have occaſionally touch'd upon the Head (as to the neceſſity of it) but that Part, and alſo the Lawfulneſs of it, has been ſo oft, and ſo well treated of (by ſome) that ſcarce any thing can be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50517:7"/>ſaid, but what would prove Repetition, which I endeavour to avoid.</p>
            <p>It may alſo be Noted as an Omiſſion, that in a Diſcourſe of this Nature, I have not ſhew'd and ſet forth particularly, how and wherein People may retrench their Expences, that ſo they may hold out the longer in paying Taxes: As for Inſtance, People ought to deny themſelves ſuch Foreign Commodities, where ſuch Trade's a Loſs and Damage to the Publick in general, tho' ſome Particular Perſons may be enrich'd thereby; and many uſeful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may be given upon this Subject of Entrenchment; but ſuch Hints may, perhaps; come ſeaſonable enough from another hand, more fit for the undertaking, tho' ſome ſhort ones ſhall be given in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Objection:</hi> Some may ſay, That this earneſt preſſing for Taxes, when the Nation's ſo low already (as if People were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in paying, to keep pace with Fancy and Imagination) ſhews, as if the Author had been kept up in ſome Retirement, or dropt lately out of the Clouds, and were altogether unacquainted with, or at leaſt, inſenſible of the State and Condition of our Nation: If he had found ſome Mine of Treaſure to pay Seſsment with, he had done ſomething to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer:</hi> There's ſcarce any diſcernable Retrenchment in the City, in ſuch ſuperfluous foreign Commodities, which Trade's a Loſs in general, both to the Publick, in wearing Ornaments, and things ſpent in Houſe-keeping; People treat and ſpend, much as they us'd to do: Nor is there any great difference in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo that paying Taxes, pinches not ſo much as People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains. And there's a Mine of Treaſure ſufficient for the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, its wants but digging out, and producing into publick Uſe: What a vaſt Quantity of uſeleſs Plate is there in the Kingdom, (as to publick Uſe) which might be employ'd, if it were come to that. What great heaps of Treaſure are there in many particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Hands, who are beſt able to pay, and yet pay leaſt of any ſort of People whatever? Perhaps, he that's worth 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> pays after the rate of 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> (and well too, as things are manag'd); in that Sum, there is 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> Loſs to the Publick, at the uſual way of Taxing Money: And is there no Remedy, but that our Laws muſt ſtill be Cob-webs, to catch the leſſer Flies, and the greater ſlip through.</p>
            <p>It ſeems alſo reaſonable, that thoſe of larger Eſtates in Lands, and great Money'd-Men, and thoſe who have great Stocks in Trade, ſhould be tax'd much deeper in the Pound rate, and for their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Stocks, than thoſe of ſmaller ſubſtances; for the former
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50517:8"/>have a Latitude and Scope to retrench, in ſuch ſuperfluous things, as above; they may alſo retrench in the Number of their Servants. A Perſon of Quality, that uſes to keep ten Servants, may be ſerv'd with five, as to all things neceſſary; and People ought to deny themſelves in ſome things, when the good of the Publick ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: If ſuch Perſons, and thoſe of the richer ſort, did ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, it would be no diminution to their eſteem and credit; there wants but ſome Examples to brake the Ice: And ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded Servants, would be much more uſeful in the Common-Wealth, by falling to ſome ſort of Work or Manuſacture, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souldiers; for we want People.</p>
            <p>But now as to thoſe of ſmall Eſtate in Land, little Money, and ſmall Trade, they ought not to bear pace, in paying with the other; for they have no room to retrench in, for ſuch keep only neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Servants, for their Husbandry and Trades, and ſpend little or nothing in the unneceſſary things above mention'd, and have but a bare Livelihood with their utmoſt Induſtry; whereas moſt of the other ſort, may pay as above, without retrenching: And if thoſe of ſmaller ſubſtance ſhould retrench, it muſt be in Meat and Drink, and their ordinary Cloathing: Now all thoſe are the Product of our own Country; therefore to abridge themſelves of ſuch, (if they could) would be a damage to the Publick, in as much, as it would cauſe a leſs Conſumption of our own Countries Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and ſo cauſe the Prices to ſink lower ſtill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second Objection:</hi> Some may ſay, what needs all this induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Arguing, to convince People of that which is ſo plain and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, to every common Underſtanding, <hi>viz.</hi> that raiſing Taxes is neceſſary at this Juncture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer:</hi> Though this be of no great Uſe to the wiſe, and prudent, yet perhaps, there may be ſome reaſonable hints to the ſecond and third, if not to the firſt rate of Readers: And yet I doubt, thoſe who pretend to be moſt convinc'd, are moſt in fault, in ſhuffling the Burden from themſelves, when it comes to the practical Part: If People could pay Taxes in Theory, by Talk and Diſcourſe, then no body would be ſlow and hang back.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third Object.</hi> The Author all along goes upon a Suppoſition, that paying a part will ſecure the reſt: Now if he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any good ſecurity for that, then People would be willing to pay the Revenue (as he hints) of a Year or two, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably for Perſonal Eſtates: But as the Caſe is, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what he has ſaid, we may pay as much as he propoſes, and yet be forc'd to pay as much more, and not then come to a thorow Settlement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50517:8"/>
               <hi>I Anſwer:</hi> If this be the general ſenſe of moſt able and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Perſons (as I believe it is) that they would be willing to pay Two years Revenue; and ſo proportionably for other Eſtates; then it ſeems they can pay ſo much: And why ſhould People ſo heavily complain? For if they can, they ought: Becauſe, as it's ſaid, in the Opinion of all the moſt Wiſe and Prudent, that's the moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way; nay, that (with good management) is the only Expedient to ſecure the reſt of our Eſtates, Liberties, Properties, and Religion it ſelf: And if ſo, then whether the Effect and Succeſs be certain, or contingent; yet the ſame Means and Method are to be purſued in hope of obtaining the end Deſign'd. Why then ſhould we be ſo ſlow and backward in raiſing Taxes, and paying our due Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince it is but what the dictates and convictions of our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon prompts us to, if we would but Hearken to them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth Objection:</hi> All this buſie promotion of great Taxes, and putting Power into the Hands of Kings, is but to ſerve a Turn, and is a ready Way to throw us into a Relapſe (before Recover'd) into the old <hi>Tory-Way</hi> of laviſhing and ſquandring away our Liberties and Properties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer:</hi> That we may preſerve our Religion, Liberties and Properties entire, were the only Reaſon that induced me to be ſo Earneſt in perſwading People into a Willingneſs to pay Taxes (though Great at preſent).</p>
            <p>Beſides, we have all the Aſſurance we can reaſonably Deſire, that His Majeſty is ſo far from ſtretching and enlarging the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative beyond its legal Limits; that His Wiſdom and Juſtice is ſuch, that He would throw back with the higheſt Reſentment, all ſuch Overplus Prerogative, as Officious and Deſigning <hi>Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> may heap upon Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Conclude All:</hi> If we would continue our Long enjoy'd dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties:</hi> If we would leave to our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities (on whom we uſually Dote with ſo much tenderneſs and paſſion) a peaceable Poſſeſſion of that, which many of us ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly have labour'd for. And above all,</p>
            <p>If we would preſerve the full exerciſe and enjoyment of that <hi>Religion,</hi> we in Appearance ſo <hi>Zealouſly Profeſs;</hi> and for which we have ſo earneſtly Contended, We ought to take the moſt probable Methods, which (next to Imploring the Divine Aid, and Living HOLY Lives) are, to <hi>Contribute Freely</hi> for a Time; and manage Faithfully and Wiſely what ſhall be ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
